RG 070:081 Second Church of Christ, Scientist (Hartford, Conn.)
Connecticut State Library
Second Church of Christ, Scientist records
1912-2002
Connecticut State Library
Second Church of Christ, Scientist (Hartford, Conn.)
8 cubic feet
The Second Church of Christ Scientist Hartford, was organized in 1907 by 11 members of The Mother Church. The first service was held on an upper floor at 64 Pearl Street, and as the congregation grew, services were moved twice to other sites. The church building at the corner of Lafayette and Russ Streets held its first service January 4, 1925. A diminished membership prompted the congregation to sell the church building to the State of Connecticut in 2008.
RG070_081
2008-035
Historical Note
The Second Church of Christ Scientist Hartford, was organized in 1907 by 11 members of The Mother Church. The first service was held on an upper floor at 64 Pearl Street, and as the congregation grew, services were moved twice to other sites. The church building at the corner of Lafayette and Russ Streets held its first service January 4, 1925. A diminished membership prompted the congregation to sell the church building to the State of Connecticut in 2008.
Source: Christian Science in Connecticut, Welcome to Second Church of Christ, Scientist Hartford, Connecticut USA! http://www.christiansciencect.org/hartford2/ (accessed May 23, 2008).
Scope and Content
Series 1, Governance is comprised mainly of two notebooks. One contains Board standing rules and votes, 1912-1990, and the other contains standing church votes, 1912-1987. Series 2, Membership includes two volumes of church meeting attendance registers, 1921-1938, a monthly envelopes register, 1935-1948, and membership lists for 1996 and 1998. Series 3, Clerk includes the clerk's files. These files contain chiefly correspondence to and from the Board of Directors as well as files for various committees. Series 3 also includes financial records including four ledgers, 1932-1955. Series 4, Committees include minutes and reports of Advertising Information Committee, Circulation Information Committee, House Committee, Literature Distribution Committee, and Sanatorium Information Committee that date primarily from the 1920s to 1960s. There are also single folders for the War Relief Committee, 1941-1945. Of note in Series 5, Sunday School are two volumes of teachers' meeting minutes, 1914-1925.
Arrangement
Series 1. Governance, 1912-1990
Series 2. Membership, 1921-1999
Series 3. Clerk, 1940-2000
Series 4. Committees, 1923-2002
Series 5. Sunday School, 1914-2001
Series 6. Procedures, 1958-1992
Series 7 Miscellaneous, 1958-2001, undated
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Second Church of Christ, Scientist (Hartford, Conn.)
Subjects:
Second Church of Christ, Scientist (Hartford, Conn.) -- Records and correspondence; Church records and registers -- Connecticut -- Hartford
Document Types:
Financial records; Membership lists; Correspondence; Reports; Minutes
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The State Library acquired these records in 2008 after the congregation sold the church building to the State of Connecticut.
Container List
- Series 1. Governance, 1912-1990
  - Board standing rules and votes, 1912-1990; 1 notebook (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Standing church votes, 1912-1987; 1 notebook (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unidentifed index, undated; 1 notebook (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 2. Membership, 1921-1999
  - Membership lists, 1996, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Monthly envelopes register, 1935-1948; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Church meeting attendance register (Box 1)
    - 1921-1928, 1 volume (Box 1)
    - 1933-1938, 1 volume (Box 1)
- Series 3. Clerk, 1940-2000
  - Clerk's Files, 1958-2000
    - Reading room correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - C.O.P. for Connecticut, 1987 December (Box 2)
    - Correspondence from Board, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence from Board, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Visiting Nursing Service (Box 2)
    - Visiting Nursing Service - Central Connecticut (Box 2)
    - C.S. Publishing Society (Box 2)
    - TMC clerk's correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Letters to the Board of Trustees from church members, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Mother Church correspondence from office of clerk, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
    - Letters from the Board of Trustees to church members, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Church appointment records - Clerk (Box 2)
    - Church meetings and Teller's Committee reports, 1991-1996 (Box 2)
    - Employee time cards (Box 2)
    - Letters to family members mostly regarding contributions in the name of a family member (Box 2)
    - Growing together workshop meeting (Box 2)
    - High Ridge House, Inc. (Box 2)
    - Board of Trustee agendas, 1982 July - 1987 September (Box 2)
    - Laurel Crest, Inc. (Box 2)
    - Directories - church worship (Box 2)
    - Johnson Publishing Company (Directory) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence from Board (Forms), 1980 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence received (Box 2)
    - Allotment checks, Request for (Box 2)
    - Appointments, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Appointment lists, 1971 July (Box 2)
    - Board of Trustees miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2)
    - Board of (Directors) Trustees, Letters to and from the Board (Box 2)
    - Bulletin boards, Church (Box 2)
    - Christian Science churches other than Hartford, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - C.O.P. for Connecticut, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Messages from Board of Trustees, 1963-1972 (Box 2)
    - Church Manufacturers Guild, Inc., Contract for rehabilitation of church pews, 1975 November (Box 2)
    - Clerks' report, 1970-1976 (Box 2)
    - Contracts (Box 2)
    - Price & Lee Hartford City Directories (Box 2)
    - Custodian time sheets (Box 2)
    - Marguerite Upson correspondence (Box 2)
    - Fowler / Fuller correspondence (Box 2)
    - Sign data (Box 2)
    - Film & broadcasting info from the Mother Church (Box 2)
    - As others see us on film, 1977 May 16 (Box 2)
    - Field assistant program, 1979 May 12 (Box 2)
    - Healing goal meeting, 1977 November, 1978 May (Box 2)
    - The Mother Church Board of Directors, 1958-1979 (Box 2)
    - C.S. Publishing Society, 1960-1978 (Box 2)
    - Maintenance workers procedures, State Dept. of Labor (Box 2)
    - Copy machine (Box 2)
    - Christian Science branch churches (Not Hartford-Glastonbury), 1980-1989 (Box 2)
    - First Church of Christ, Scientist, Hartford, 1971-1989 (Box 2)
    - First Church of C.S. Longmeadow, Mass. - Sharing Church Comm., Big E activities (Box 2)
    - Reports annual meeting, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Committee reports, 1988 October 17 (Box 2)
    - Committee reports, 1974 April, May, October, November (Box 3)
    - Church Committee appointments, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
    - Lecture folder, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Lecture preparatory meeting worldwide (Box 3)
    - Church lending library - Hymnal Committee (Box 3)
    - Literature Distribution Committee, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
    - Clerk-Treasurer Monitor Committees, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
    - Youth Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - C.S. Committee for institutional work in Conn. bylaws and correspondence (Box 3)
    - House Committee reports, 1974 (Box 3)
    - House Committee petty cash reports, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Pigeon Control Committee (Box 3)
    - House Committee, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
    - House Committee applications, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - House Committee, 1980-1980 (Box 3)
    - House Committee reports, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Sunday School, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Orin E. Carpenter, C.S.B. Assc. (Box 3)
    - The Mother Church reading rooms (Box 3)
    - Usher (Box 3)
    - Lending Library / Hymnal (Box 3)
    - C.S. joint media project WOR (Box 3)
    - Neighborhood communications (Box 3)
    - Usher (Box 3)
    - WOR radio joint church lecture (Box 3)
    - Sunday School weekend (Box 3)
    - "Among the Branches" (Box 3)
    - Hartford Courant ads (Box 3)
    - CL&P (Box 3)
    - Custodian duties (Box 3)
    - All committee chairmen (Box 3)
    - Care facilities - Info re establishing (Box 3)
    - Child Care Committee (Box 3)
    - College organization information, 1966-1973 (Box 3)
    - A-Z correspondence files, 23 folders (Box 3)
    - Typewriter - Epson (Box 4)
    - Typewriter - Juki - Sierra (Box 4)
    - Mr. Skarie - Special meeting (Box 4)
    - Publishing Society, The C. S. (Box 4)
    - Clerk's office (Box 4)
    - Films and tapes, TMC B & P order forms (Box 4)
    - Monitor endowment fund (Box 4)
    - Videoconference, 1984 December 8 (Box 4)
    - House Committee, 1973 (Box 4)
    - House Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence from clerk, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
    - Church Activities, Dept. of - The Mother Church (Box 4)
    - Annual meeting of the Mother Church regarding videotape (Box 4)
    - Annual meeting, 1983 (Box 4)
    - General correspondence to Second Church, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Reports - Metaphysical Committee, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Letters from Board of Trustees Clerk, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
    - Letters to the Board of Trustees from members of the Second Church, 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Letters to the Board of Trustees from church members, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Letters to the Board of Trustees from other than church members, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - annual committee reports, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - annual committee reports, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - annual committee reports, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - annual committee reports, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - semi-annual committee reports, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - semi-annual committee reports, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - semi-annual committee reports, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - semi-annual committee reports, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Church meeting - semi-annual committee reports, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut Committee on Publication, 1990-1994 (Box 4)
    - Reading room correspondence (Box 4)
    - House Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Lecture Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Literature Distribution Committee, 1980-1989 (Box 4)
    - Christian Science Reading Room reports, 1990-1995 (Box 4)
    - Ushering staff, 1978-1984 (Box 4)
    - Christian Science Reading Room - correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940, 1988-1999, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
  - Correspondence - sample letters, 1970-1993, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records, 1928-1998
    - Bills paid, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 12-36)
      Arranged by check number.
    - Collections and petty cash book, 1928-1998 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Ledgers, 1932-1955 (Box 6)
      - 1932 September - 1937 April, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1937 May - 1943 May, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1943 June - 1949 August, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1949 September - 1955 November, 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Insurance papers, 1944-1946, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Petty cash, 1990-1995 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Sales slips, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Vouchers, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Voucher lists, 1987-1996 (Box 7, Folder 32-35)
  - Handbook, 1992-2000, undated (Box 7, Folder 9-11)
  - Interest/Occupation card file (Box 5)
- Series 4. Committees, 1923-2002
  - Appointments, 1991-1999 (Box 7, Folder 36-47)
  - Appointments, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Lists, 1980-1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Blank appointment forms, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Advertising Committee/Promotion Committee/Extension Work Committee minutes (Box 8)
    - Minutes, 1923-1928; 1 volume (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Advertising Information Committee (Box 8)
    - Advertising records, 1945-1950 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Bulletin board photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - Lists of articles covering 1917 through 1938 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Lists of members, 1944-1950 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, 1928-1950, undated (Box 8, Folder 12-19)
    - Mission, 1924-1931 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Reports to Board of Directors, 1946-1954 (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
    - Reports to Board on regular and special meetings, special letters and lists, 1940-1943 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Service Bulletins, 1942 July - 1943 November (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Circulation Information Committee (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1966, undated (Box 8, Folder 25-27)
    - Correspondence with Board of Directors, 1950-1965 (Box 8, Folder 28-29)
    - Correspondence on news stands, 1950-1957, undated (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Display photographs, 1938-1944, undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Newsletters, 1958-1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Notebook, 1958-1975 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Pamphlets, undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Promotional material, undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Receipts, 1954-1958 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Reports to Board of Directors, 1950-1966 (Box 8, Folder 38-41)
    - Semi-annual reports, 1950-1966 (Box 8, Folder 42-43)
  - Finance Committee (Box 8)
    - Reading room, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - House Committee (Box 8)
    - Agendas, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Minutes, 1930-1940; 1 volume (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Reports to Board of Directors, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Literature Distribution Committee (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1934-1960 (Box 8, Folder 49-54)
    - Financial statements, 1944-1959 (Box 8, Folder 55-57)
    - Lecture orders, 1951-1959 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Minutes, 1923-1939 (Box 8, Folder 59-61)
    - Minutes, 1940-1959 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9)
    - Orders, 1944-1960, undated (Box 9, Folder 6-11)
    - Reports to Board of Directors, 1946-1953 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
  - Sanatorium Information Committee (Box 9)
    - Minutes, 1935-1955 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - War Relief Committee, 1941-1945 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Series 5. Sunday School, 1914-2001
  - Attendance cards, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Attendance cards, 1996-2001 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Attendance notebook, 1994-2001 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Camp lists, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Loan library borrowers' cards, circa 1991-1997 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Procedures, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Rules of the Sunday school, 1979; 1 pamphlet (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Teachers' meeting minutes, 1914-1918 February; 1 volume (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Teachers' meeting minutes, 1918 May - 1925; 1 volume (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Visitors' cards, circa 1982-2000 (Box 9, Folder 25)
- Series 6. Procedures, 1958-1992
  - Helpful information for readers (Box 9)
    - 1958 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - 1963 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - 1983, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Schedule of work to be done in and around church by week days, 1967 August 15 (Box 9, Folder 29)
- Series 7 Miscellaneous, 1958-2001, undated
  - Christian Science activities a the World's Fair, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Photograph album of church interior, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Picture card set, Christian Science Pavilion, World's Fair, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Posters giving church and reading room hours, undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Proclamations for Public Thanksgiving, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Responses by Committee on Publications and others to September 11 attacks in New York City, 2001 September-October (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Real estate marketing book + text of 1930 article describing church building, circa 2007 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    The Real estate marketing book was created to interest potential buyers.
    It shows interior views of the church and exterior views of the church and surrounding area.
  - Theodore Wise letter against the M.B.E. library, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Views of the world headquarters, Boston, Mass., 1974 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Christian Science Monitor 50th Anniversary 1908-1958 sticker (Box 10)
  - Sunday School Free Circulating Library sign (Box 10)
  - Engraving plates, 4 items (Box 10)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1996 June 6; 3 copies (Box 10)
  - Christian Science subject cards (Box 10)